[Music]
so I am my name is Professor Thorstein
Percy and I'm a professor of psychiatry
and psychotherapy in Germany at Hannover
medical school and another institution
and I have been interested in
psychedelic drugs and altered states of
consciousness of different origin since
40 years meanwhile and I have conducted
research in that rhythm for like 30
years including clinical studies with
different psychedelic substances and
other means of inducing altered states
of consciousness what was your interest
in the mind before then what really what
really got you even moving this
direction in life so I was a kind of
natural scientist and an atheist at
first and then I began to study
philosophy and I was doing fishing and
looking at floats for hours and in this
context I got a mystical experience
spontaneously and being being one with
nature and having great feelings and
very elaborate kind of sorts and so I
this was a kind of life transforming
experience but in the harsh sense so I
needed kind of three years to integrate
that experience was it irritated my view
of the world view in such a fundamental
way that I was completely irritated I
even had to get psychotherapy to
integrate that one experience which I
have immediately felt to be the most
merciful experience a human can get that
was an intuition or an immediately
immediate recognition worthy experience
you say good experience yeah it was a
mystical experience of being one with
nature and stuff like that and that was
very impressive and so therefore I had
and life-transforming a process going on
and later on because I studied I was a
philosopher at that point and so I began
to study about mystical experience and
what they mean and what the implications
are and later on how they can be
generated because usually is we have
them or you have them not this is a more
random matter kind of thing if you're
not a nun or yes Zen master or something
and even they don't have it always and
yet so therefore I came across the
option that drugs might be helpful to to
induce his kind of experiences and well
I was lucky enough to have such an
psilocybin induced experience early on
which was also a mystical experience a
full-blown mystic experience might have
been kind of a revival of what I have
experienced before and at that point I
had the very deep intuition that my life
will be devoted to the mystical
experience or exploring the mystical
experience the mystical realm as well as
psychedelic drugs very interesting so
how old were you when that first
mystical experience first you think I
was kind of eighteen eighteen how rigid
was your mind by eighteen because you
say you were an atheist yeah would you
say would you describe yourself as
someone who really did need to box
things up in a way that we might
associate with someone who likes
mechanism you know and an answer exactly
so I was not very much in contact on
contact with my feelings and I was also
having these typical kind of adolescent
crises where you don't know who you are
and your identity is still something you
have to figure out and so on and
therefore I think
I got very much irritated because I was
already in a kind of lab Isle a kind of
state and we're looking out for
where are the fragments of my identity
and and that process made me very how
should I say very open but at the same
point of time very fragile the state of
suggestibility that psychedelics /
people into and the fact that they can
disorient someone you know at this
fundamental level which which I really
think at one level needs to be referred
to with a mystical language with more
metaphysical language you know changing
that around for someone what does that
mean for not only what they think about
the world but importantly how they're
going to act in it how they're going to
treat other people
whatever fluence they're going to have
in other people and what that ultimately
means for society but before I suppose
we can really talk about that properly
you'd have to have a conversation about
you know yeah what what society is and
what have you so okay so so you have
this experience and then you have the
psychotherapy what was it about the
psychotherapy that helped integrate that
experience for you you know one thing
was it we've elaborating partially on
this experience and I made further
experience during the course of the
psychotherapy somewhat and we also could
integrate this experience and so at last
I've and it also helped me to overcome
all these frigid fragility and
'la by honest and and these fragmented
kind of things and it was very very
helpful because usually if you are an
adolescence parents can't help you as
effective in that respect so it's good
if you have another person you have an
intimate relationship with and which is
really looking out for you when and can
help you when you with you in your
issues yeah was it was it a man and a
woman no it was a man it was a man okay
these days in psychotherapy particularly
when it comes to psychedelics they have
the man and the woman yeah do you have
thoughts about that and whether that's
important yeah it is important from an
archetypical point of view because you
have to have both so to say as a usual
thing but what is also on my mind is
that it was produced this kind of
setting by cases of abuse sexual abuse
with people in the early work with MDMA
and the early 1980s when they had two
cases which are widely known became
widely known and there are some issues
with kind of making people more open by
these drugs more labile which can be
helpful in therapeutic processing but it
can be also helpful in producing abuse
you know it's said using the therapist
to abuse a patient another aspect is
also that sometimes especially if it
comes to MDMA if you give em be made to
a patient's to a patient he might get
rid of his neurotic fears for some hours
and so you will see you got a company
get a completely other impression from
the other person he might show up as a
completely lovely individual with a lot
of potentials and stuff like that
so you might fell in love in fact with a
patient because of seeing him in a
completely different fashion and so
there is a certain specific risk
involved about these kind of things and
I think having a couple there there the
installs a lot of social control about
these kind of issues and therefore they
don't come up
for me where that links up with in a in
another tangential way and we will
rescue the thread it's just that when
you engage in in the kind of vulnerable
a vulnerable relationship with someone
way where you are speaking well
authentically to that place of
vulnerability and then with an attitude
towards change with with the potential
for help it's a bit of creativity
involved in that you know it is it seems
to me at least like that something
similar to that mechanism is what's
involved in developing a genuine
romantic relationship you know and it's
you have to it's quite it's quite
interesting to watch that in yourself as
you go about life in general because
because you might want to be a very
honest person and an engaged with with
with those kind of interactions and to
it and and ultimately you should be an
honest person and otherwise you pervert
your relationship to being and it almost
terribly buddy wrong for you but but
there is still there is still
appropriate places within then to be
guarded in a certain way if you want to
protect yourself or part of something
that is unconscious in you so from a
man's perspective if you're going to be
young and about it that animal you know
getting too attached to a particular
individual you have to you have to be
you have to do have to watch out to what
it is you are latching you are latching
onto and I can totally understand how in
a therapeutic setting you've got a
psychodynamic there that you know you
have to watch out for it's very very
interesting mm-hmm yeah so okay so you
have um so you have the psychotherapy as
it as it between 18 and 20 watch now
what about the philosophical side of you
because of course you might have had a
probably quite a say as an 18 year old
if I think back to what I was doing a
very naive attitude towards the world we
could maybe call it a naive materialism
of course in the 20th century you have
behaviorism very much in vogue so what
was it that that that intellectually or
philosophically gave you the new
grounding or a new space to explore in
that you could place the context of your
attitude towards the world in so it's
somewhat deepened my understanding as a
consequence but not out of the
experience itself it more indirectly
because I dig deeper and I had a much
more broader scope and I don't know if
that
used by these mystical experiences but I
have very concise concedes concise
thoughts yes and as and also concise
writing yes and elaborations about
things but I a kind of attempt to stay
away from a certain point of view it
means I'm not a materialist I'm not an
idealist I'm not a duelist I respect all
these approaches but I don't have to
hang on one of them yes this is I don't
know how I became that much detached off
from that but it is more general
attitude in my mind and I was also
fought by people because of that because
they want to make me they will say
something oh I'm a duelist I'm this I'm
believing in afterlife and all that kind
of stuff but I my personal approach as a
psychiatrist psychotherapists
psychologists philosopher is more like I
respect that humans have the experience
of telepathy if it's real or not it
doesn't matter to me so my research is
limited to the experience and so we can
look out for example if gymnastic
teachers have more OBEs than others for
example because they have a more
awareness of their body scheme and stuff
like that other you know yeah we can if
we can find out a lot by just exploring
the experience we don't have to talk
about if it's real or not but the people
tend to have these simple things like
mind over matter
that's all debate you know there is some
influence of the mind there is some
influence on the matter so where's the
problem you don't have to be so much
polarized right yes I do understand
where you're coming from
as someone who has engaged in a bit of
philosophy of mind I suppose it is an
interest of mine to try and be as clear
as possible about what we mean by matter
and mean by mind and and well perhaps we
can get into that later I am quite
influenced by I suppose the process
philosophers bugs on whitehead
but also Peter Peter our friend
people will have seen him on the podcast
so some variety of pants like is and
it's quoting quite interesting to me you
know and and the reason for that as well
is because because I do find the
psychological fact the experience so
important yeah
oh that in actual fact well when you
follow it when you follow it deep I mean
as Jung did the line all of a sudden
between psychological fact and perhaps
metaphysical process it does begin to
blur in an interesting way
if you accept certain metaphysical
things and I I do quite like I do feel a
resonance with pursuing an integration
of Jung and the more process philosophy
approach and I think it might bear fruit
but okay okay so there's there's a few
things I I definitely know I want to
cover with you today yeah the first I
suppose is to speak to where we are
wrapped currently right now we're
upstairs backstage at be on psychedelics
conference and it's it's been a very
interesting few days sometimes sometimes
threatening to be too interesting but
not quite always always interesting in a
way I could manage almost every
interaction you have with someone you
know it's quite profound yeah people are
very very switched on yeah
very interested in in the mind and
metaphysics yeah but what's also
interesting to me and what I will ask
you about yeah is it's the general
attitude and movement and intention of
the collective of people that are
brought here in your from your
perspective what is the where do you see
this psychedelic community what is what
is what is what is there what is the
dominant attitude towards psychedelics
like what is driving people's interest
here do you think you have different
patterns going on I think one is that
you have freaky adolescence always I
mean even three thousand thirty thousand
years ago they had these kind of
identities seeking
irritated individuals in this adolescent
phase let's save 15 to 25 kind of and
the people are much more open to kind of
new experiences maybe even visionary
experience psychedelics and so on if you
look at the tribes in their former times
or isolated in Brazil or wherever you
will see that the people are much more
having much more affinity to have these
new and maybe irritating experiences to
to clear up where they have to go what
their personal paths will be and stuff
like that so you have that segment
always we had that since the nineteen
sixties it was more explicit but we have
that since that time you know maybe not
as much in the former Eastern European
countries which are catching up right
now but in a lot of other countries and
so it is kind of natural that the people
look out or search for these kind of
experience irritating experiences that's
one part I think it's a big part of it
yes yeah as yesterday on the fireplace
I've seen these kind of people yes and
but on the other side you have much more
majored people which are kind of 35 to
55 or something and they have a more
elaborate interest in the topic which is
much more fundamental in that sense that
they got influenced by the experiences
and you also have a lot of people which
kind of happening having sorts and
attitude like somebody might call a
naive utopianism like oh we can be a
lovely community blah blah you know but
kind of dissolving boundaries so far
that there the differences become
blurred kind of and what I realized you
might do that more easily as a physician
because if you believe that the people
you see represent humanity then you
might think Oh everybody's ill because
the doctor is just consulted if the
person's are ill if you are working ten
hours in a clinic you see ten hours
it'll people you
saying okay everybody's ill this is not
true this is a kind of perceptual
selection bias and this is also true for
these tiny psychedelic conferences so
there's just one conference this year
explicitly designed for representing
psychedelic psychedelic researchers as
humanity human sciences about
psychedelics this is here so we are out
of five billions I think we have a few
hundred here so we have to be careful
that we don't take this tiny little bit
for a new wave or something like that
but on the other side what we reach
right now kind of unexpectedly is that
psychedelics may have a revival in
psychiatry and that might lead to some
consequences because what we have seen
through the studies during the last ten
years is that even the mystical
experience which is really alien to our
countries and the masses might be
helpful in treating depression and if
that's true mystical experience might
become quite more popular that's a
possibility and if we look more
neutrally at them we might realize that
they are very versatile experiences and
that a lot of people should have access
to them and not this kind of random like
I had by chance thing and that might
lead in the long run to a more open
attitude about these experiences and
might be even helped to integrate these
kind of experiences much more in our
culture which also implies much more
people having them yes there's another
side as many sides of the psychedelic
world and one side I know as a
particular interest of yours is the
micro dosing side of psyche terms and
micro dosing is where you take a sub
perceptual dose of your psychedelics now
here people have different attitudes
about this so my first question would be
what are the dominant attitudes that you
see arising in the
about the use of micro dosing different
psychedelics yeah so one thing is that
you can't inspire the usual population
doing that because it's still an illegal
scheduled substance absolutely there
there might be some risks induced and
people are will be skeptical anyway so
we are talking about a psychedelic user
population which is already using these
kind of things and I think there are a
lot of aspects about that one is or one
major aspect is that you can take a
psychedelic on a more regular basis
without having all these irritating
distracting effects and so therefore a
lot of people think oh I can do LSD
without getting as a risk of being
fragmented or getting on a horror trip
or getting a mystical experience you
know the kind of risk minimization in
the understanding of the people that's
one aspect another aspect is that these
substances might do something to the
human organism which might be good even
if we don't doze them so much that we
have these psychological alterations is
that this it from a pharmacological
point and I'm a pharmacologist to this
might be possible but this is there's up
to now no reliable AB evidence to my
eyes that it is really the case this is
not that all the reports are not true
but they are still anecdotal might have
been placebo induced and so on so we
still don't know exactly from a
scientific point of view if this is
really a method which can alter whatever
kind of thing like a creativity creative
thinking stuff like that what we know is
you can't utter creative singing or your
thoughts or your thought patterns if you
are not doing a dose which is uttering
your thought patterns if you use a dose
which is sub perceptual it means you
can detect it and so you can't detect
changes in your thoughts so this is
beyond the definition what I would like
to introduce here is that when I have
written the recent book which I have
written about my as a science of micro
dosing I came across a kind of 50
studies in the past which have been done
with very low doses nobody knows about
that the whole internet is free of that
there's no knowledge and this is how the
Internet can generate illusions because
they people don't look at the past
anymore they are just in the now which
is mindful but maybe idiotic in another
sense that they ignore the past and they
don't know about and what we know from
these early studies is that above 20
micrograms you get a certain kind of
effect which might in some rare cases in
behave in a way that people might become
a little more creative but I would bet
that because of individuals and sative
ities about the substance even if he
would dose them within quality known and
purity known stuff and could give
everybody 20 micrograms or let's say 30
or something they would still have
completely different reactions somewhat
and so therefore it's very hard to dose
in the room what I call above 20
micrograms where you get some kind of
effect I would like to call that mini
dosing coming from 20 to 50 and a lot of
the people which have micro dosed in the
past for example about Huisman the
discoverer of LSD has done in a more or
less erratic fashion let's say five to
seven times a year at maximum he did 30
to 90 milli micro grams and that is
quite a different deal then you have
some effects it's not a full-blown
experience yes we know from recent
research that the full blown LSD
experience needs 200 micrograms then you
have the full-blown effects
if you go lower you have less effects
it's not a bad thing it might be even
good but we still have to define where
what micro dozing in that sense is yes
it's really tough isn't it I mean it's
tough to get a grip on what the full LSD
experience would really be I mean do you
mean to refer to the peak breakthrough
mystical experiences okay you know no
it's it's just that we know from the
question your profiles yes and from
clinical experience that you don't get
much more if you get a higher dose and
you get somewhat less if you take a
lower dose so we know that all the
responses on these questionnaires they
got maximum activated when you have that
kind of those and you got much less if
you get lower doses okay so but that
doesn't mean like with a car you can run
200 miles let's say with an sports car
but you usually run 50 right and so if
it's a speed of 50 is much more usable
for you in the average day then running
200 you know you know what I'm talking
about yes so it doesn't mean that a
hundred micrograms for example can do a
lot in respect to psychotherapeutic
processing which might you which might
be not as optimal with a full dose yes
and so therefore I'm not discriminating
lower dosages or something yes no
absolutely I mean it's one thing for me
that other eye that I not quite seeing
as much in conversation about
psychedelics is really what the
fundamental aim is whether whether it's
for an individual's life or a collective
now people are talking about that it's
not like people aren't interested in
aims of course and as far as therapeutic
goals go well obviously it's it's it's
dealing with trauma in such a way that
it no longer holds back the individual
and causes them some degree of suffering
it's it's it's integrating that in such
a way that something can be learned from
there so that they don't repeat the same
cycle of of bad behave
d habituates you know it can take away
that the negative self narrative and
that's all that's all good right there I
can understand how if someone's got a
wound they're in a physiological sense
we can roughly help it out but but in
terms of in terms of really patterns of
behavior to aim at in life that there
are that are good well I guess the the
point I'm making is that the experience
you're going to have on psychedelics is
in part determined by how you are
actually living and what you are doing
not only what your intention is for the
day if it's writing if it's you know if
you want to have if you're going to do
an exam and you take a really high dose
of LSD it's going to be tough for you to
maintain the right kind of coherence
often so obviously there's certain tool
for a time in place but I guess what
does concern me I suppose is is
exploration for explorations sake at
when that exploration isn't
fundamentally in an important sense
grounded to something vital in the home
that itself is the base from which the
very image of what to move towards is
projected so it's kind of a Union idea
the idea of the god image in which in
one sense is combination of the
conscious and unconscious psychic life
but in another sense I guess the the
grounds from which the image of what is
missing in the psyche or or what is
missing in the individual is projected
into the future innocence is the goal to
which individuation moves like you can't
really have movement without a goal
otherwise it's sort of static inkay like
oh sorry it's a sort of chaotic so I
know this is a fairly I'm sort of
throwing things out here and but but
what I'm concerned with most of all is
is that what is good in our culture's is
involved in coordinating to some degree
our aims for using psychedelics is that
I mean Oh am I making myself somewhat
clear with at least the importance of
thinking about things this way does this
like in a helpful way of thinking so if
it if it comes to what also might be
called after or with Abraham Maslow the
self-actualization it has some some
parallels to the innovative iteration
process allow young yes but I would
think that you can have different
approaches in that respect so if you for
example expand your consciousness by a
psychedelic substance you might become
aware of reams of yourself your
relationships and your
self-actualization process or your
individuation process yes which you
might have neglected before there could
be one thing so that could be
potentially enriching if you can
integrate the risk in a responsible way
you can integrate these parts which you
have had neglect neglect it before but
it also HEIs ins your responsibilities
we have to think about that the other
thing is if you are not becoming
conscious of your neglect because you're
using the drug to avoid realizing new
your neglects and we see that somewhat
more than the appropriate way to handle
these kind of experiences and to allow
them so there's also something which an
skarner the major pioneer of psycholytic
therapy in the 1960s until the 80s and
he said to me when I learned with him
and he said you know we have sometimes
these patients which have these avoiding
enjoyment so they enjoy the experience
by avoiding the problematic part of it
they avoid the neglect they avoid their
dark sides they avoid insights into
their relationship problems and so on
and so on and so in the psychedelic
culture in fact if you look at this
partially crude settings where the
protects the drugs it's mostly music and
a lot of outside stimuli so that they
don't come to a meditative attitude
where you can evaluate yourself maybe
from a higher kind of perspective of the
higher self also so that you really can
make conclusions and having insights and
and experiences which really broaden
your scope you know a lot of times for
example if you have an at Tibetan clan
Shaolin this is Tibetan belts you know
going going on you know it gives you a
very smooth sound you know this is
completely different if it comes to your
personal attention about yourself that
might be helpful but if you here for
example tape with Jimi Hendrix you might
put your attention only on the lead
guitar so it's a completely different
deal and this is why a lot of people I
would say 80% of the users of
psychedelics don't profit from the
experience at as much because they use
it in a very extroverted way and having
a lot of stimuli from the outside having
open eyes they don't go they simply
don't go inside so they avoid the inside
which is the original purpose to do
psychedelics but we also have to be
tolerant about ecstatic experiences in
general so they generate ecstatic
experiences but without realising what
they can do with themselves on the drugs
let me just finish these thoughts with
one thing kind of 10 years ago they
interviewed the major techno DJ in
Germany and at the last point in the
interview they said to him is there
anything you want to say to the people
from your side and from your heart and
he said yeah the essence is take MDMA at
home close your eyes have a place in bed
and here soft music this is my
recommendation because this kind of
experience what you can get from Emily
May for example or even LSD and they
avoid by having these very loud and
stimulating outside stimuli dominated
settings
he has very very interesting very
interesting let me let me try and get at
this idea which you've helped illuminate
slightly it's I guess what I'm trying to
do is actually work through something I
can't articulate properly but we are
here where we are so and and and the
idea is that well it would be it would
be to speculate as to why people might
be resistant to really look with him and
now of course there is a lot to say here
and I don't mean to encapsulate it all I
mean - I mean to speak to a small
fragment of it and that would be that
you know there are lots of things about
how we live and how we process that can
appear arbitrary if you become
disoriented from the deeper patterns of
action that they are actually involved
in supporting you know an experience I
had not long ago and this is an
extroverted experience I suppose to some
degree but I was walking along and and
there was a guy driving his car you know
and it was an old quite beautiful car
but I'm sure he was doing the same old
things that everybody else does with
cars you know use it to get from home to
work and he's got dinner later on and
then he goes about his day and there I
am on LSD sort of disoriented from the
at least they're phenomenally present
realization of the normal way to be you
know I mean you see things for their
slightly arbitrary nature and the
concern might be it to make this more
slightly more mystical and psychological
than I can properly speak to is that
well I think people sometimes mistake in
some cases the necessary actions that we
do to keep society functioning to keep
our lives working
because we do actually have important
cares whether it's to to to maintain the
health of our family or ourselves or or
our community we are agents in a grander
pattern of collective behavior that
needs to function in a certain way to
continue not falling into chaos and and
the concern is that sometimes when you
look within even it should be fine you
lose orientation to to the thing you
really you really shouldn't
and then people suddenly feel like oh
I'm off you know I'm it so it's okay to
be decentralized or that's all bad
that's also stupid why are we doing it
you know and I wonder I wonder if that's
because in some sense we are detached
from ultimately a symbolic relationship
some kind of deeper symbolic
relationship to our culture let me check
on that camera though
okay Torsten we are back minor technical
difficulties difficulties again yeah
yeah where my mind is at now has gone
from well I suppose it's mainly at
burgers we've been talking about some
burgers here they're charging a little
bit too much actually in my opinion but
it's fine I mean people have got to make
their money so I was talking about the
concern I have
when psychedelic experience can to an
individual reveal a kind of arbitrary
nature to some of our beliefs and
actions and then also sometimes throw
the baby out with the bathwater in
respect of the ultimately vital and
living and important grandeur structure
of patterns of behavior that are good
that those ideas or that those
experiences can jar against so you can
comment on that if you like or I suppose
you can tell me about anything you have
in particular to say about what people
should be wary of in psychedelic
experience when they look within and
perhaps talk about why it is that
sometimes people don't wish to engage in
their inner life so I think I'll start
by there by going on something what you
mentioned which is that people who don't
have the usual concepts in their mind
when they are on a psychedelic drug and
I think that is a really under
researched area of psychedelic
experiences that because the brain is
somewhat irritated you don't have your
usual conceptual knowledge available to
evaluate things in the outer world and
but it also frees you somewhat from the
concept so you can see much more of the
things you you see because you're not
kind of putting concepts onto them ok
this is a bird of this kind this is that
person this is a
camera and so on you can look with much
more than a kind of open mind or open
perception at things because you don't
connect them too much to your previous
experience by using contact concepts to
to evaluate them or or to to get hold of
them now or to to see what purpose they
have or if they are dangerous or not and
stuff like that this can be very
interesting to to be beyond human
concepts and then there can be even a
much deeper kind of perception going on
what you can realize when you encounter
an animal on a psychedelic truck I mean
if you are honest like under the
influence of a psychedelic drug like LSD
or so then you are beyond to your usual
concepts that means you might not
perceive an wild pick in the forest as a
danger which in usually it is it is not
a real danger right but people are
anxious about them they think oh they
are wild we are not wild so me we must
must have been anxious in or we we have
to be anxious about as a danger which is
coming from their enemy so if you are
under the influence of LSD for example
and the wasp would sit down you know on
your nose you are not anxious you would
look it up and say oh an interesting MA
hey man I've never seen something so
near and stuff like that so you are
potentially in mutton much more respect
of the other creatures because you are
not determined to look out for your
survival like is it a danger or can I
can I eat it you know like these kind of
categorizing is beyond your scope and
that means you're looking much more at
the animal life as it is represented in
this species as it is in you and so you
see much more commonalities in between
the species and even might be with the
plants and the mushrooms
you know then a dissimilarities or
you you you're not into using the world
your much more into perceiving the world
and you would see much more
connectedness and commonalities that way
and I think it is very important under
research that we go beyond concepts even
the only the neuropsychological
experiments are much more to look at is
your intelligence score going down and
are you having less selective attention
stuff like that you know but the
interesting thing is that you get rid of
selective attention because you get rid
of your concepts so if you think oh this
this light there might be a car so you
are looking at it coming and then you
realize oh yeah it has a trunk it has
another light and you know has has all
these features so your perception is
kind of and your attention is kind of
guided by your concepts and so if you
get rid of the concept you might also
have another kind of attention which is
much more broad in scope and takes much
more things into as significant as it
would have been if you are tightened to
your concepts and you got a much smaller
realm of evaluating things and
perceiving things so it would seem to me
that there's a positive component to
that experience but also a negative
component as well do you recognize
positives and negatives with exactly for
example there's one example which I like
to quote which was an experience my
girlfriend had tens of years ago they
were sitting together having an LSD trip
I think about five people and one guy
was playing a guitar an acoustic guitar
and he didn't had a plectrum he used a
piece of an broken bottle right and so
by chance he opened his artery in the in
the forearm and the blood was
going flowing out there and it was an
immediate life-threatening danger
but the other people there looking at
him and said oh man what a nice color
what a nice thing is going on there you
know they were not into their concepts
about dangerous and it's an artery and
that can be and so often so he didn't
call up anybody
they didn't even help him for a while at
a certain point they realize okay there
is something wrong and this guy hold his
hand there and stuff and though they
helped him and he was rescued but the
first minutes they didn't realize what
what happened there yes and this can be
dangerous dangerous but if you are in a
protected environment it shouldn't be a
problem because if you would just have
matrices lying around and stuff like
that so I mean where should be the
danger coming from right might come from
your own inner space could be aggression
or something like that but these are
very rare occasions and you say show up
in therapeutic setting settings you can
easily handle these kind of things as a
therapist tip yeah that's interesting so
that's a good example of of a danger of
the sort of external world my suppose
but what about when someone is looking
within and I guess the immediate well
that the ordinary function of how you
relate to yourself is changed we talk
about ego dissolution oh no I mean
there's lots of different ways to think
about that one might be that there's an
almost hope there can be an almost total
annihilation of what it is to usually
relate yourself to yourself and and so
but experience remains and and you will
encounter images you know and I use that
term very broadly but could you talk to
perhaps what it is to gaze inward from
that space where your ordinary look
relation to concepts changes and then
but also talk to what what the pitfall
might be like what is the resistance
people have to looking within there
because we know not everybody's art or
big questions so the first thing is
these drugs were immediately called
consciousness expanding by early
researchers already and we know that
from the shamans that they also have a
kind of view on the substances like okay
the expanse your capacity to perceive
yourself and it is not just that you put
your attention inward you could do that
with meditation or other things too
which might becomes a reputed in that
sense to in some cases but what the
difference is with the psychedelics to
my eyes is that a psychedelic stimulate
is a brain and that means that they even
if there are some regions which are not
having as much blood as usual and that
irritates the brain to the general
consensus is that you have an a very
much increase of inner stimuli
production and so all these kind of
dreamlike states what your people
experience are coming from these
increase of production of inner stimuli
and I think with this kind of day
dreamlike flow of imagery and
experiences you can experience much more
of yourself but but there is a certain a
threatening thing in that too because
you don't know in which kind of corner
of yourself you will end at last and
what you will confront and this is
especially what I like because then you
don't suggest so much to the patient
it's more like a process which he is
doing by himself with some support of
you so if it comes to hypnosis for
example you are much more suggestive you
are much more potentially manipulative
and your concepts guides the experience
stuff like that and with psycholytic
syrup or psychedelic therapy you are not
really impregnating the person and
you're not really guiding you're more
kind of a moderator you were kind of
helper in some cases you might say okay
it's better if you stay on your mattress
if it's a person is tending to stand up
in a dysfunctional fashion so
you happen and in other things you can
converse with him you can calm him down
stuff like that but let the inner
process happen this is a kind of
paradigm in psycho lytic and psychedelic
therapy so don't intervene as much and I
this is very much what I like about this
kind of a therapeutic work that the
healing is coming from within I even
called it that way the healing from
coming from within you know and that
means you're just a moderator this is
also where you can see there is a kind
of distinction between the psychotic
psychedelic therapist one try to tend to
further their narcissism means
oh I'm the healer I'm the guy who is
directing the experience I am the guy
who is giving the substances I'm see my
God and stuff like that and the others
become through experience with a service
sarap utak work they become more and
more humble and realize that the people
heal mainly heal themselves and we are
just moderating self-healing capacities
yes very very interesting
so is it part of your role to sit in on
the administration of psycho lytic
therapy yeah I have done that quite a
lot and I'm still doing it occasionally
but we not we are now approaching the
stage of the psychedelic revival where
we are doing a therapeutic studies and
so in the near future we will be able to
sit again in legal settings but I have
done that already with sons Colonna and
with Swiss guys which has permit in the
early 1990s and so I have a lot gathered
a lot of experience with sitting with
patience yes yes that's really very
interesting have you been
have you been influenced a tool by Stan
graphs work yeah definitely so
especially in the beginning because it
was giving you a more broader outlook on
the experiences you can get
in but in retrospect I would say it was
already there by other researchers but
much more dispersed in the literature
and so he putted it together and he also
came from the psycholytic approach which
was more inspired by psychoanalysis and
lower dosages in serial sessions and so
we had very much knowledge of both
approaches the psychedelic approach with
one or two doses and high high doses and
inducing life transforming mystical
experiences and as well as with the
psycholytic approach he also was ideal
to give us a more broader picture of the
psychedelic or cytolytic Serra poetic
processes because he was also part of
two cultures the American culture and
the Czech culture of the European
culture in essence and so therefore he
was the ideal guy to put all that
together he had also a very good
education in the theory of science yes
and so but I have to confess it as a
later a work of him I was not as much
impressed by but this is not just my
personal thing I think the first work
was most important to lay the groundwork
for something like transpersonal
psychology and respecting much more
these life transforming aspects of the
psychedelic experience okay so that book
his first great major work is realms of
the human unconscious that's correct
yeah it is it is a really quite
remarkable book actually for people who
are curious about the LSD experience
there's quite remarkable accounts of
some of his patients and also a very
detailed analysis of the various stages
or classes of kinds of experience as he
sees them as a problem for before was
that a lot of the psychiatrist and
psychotherapist we're kind of shy to
talk about these experiences even and
they were not able to conceptualize them
and not as comprehensively as a stan has
done that and therefore he kind of
blocks away for these
kind of psychological experiences to be
respected not be called psychotic or
strange or alien or whatever and we also
had mahants calendar for example was
much more technical in his descriptions
and he in his letter yes he told me he
had kind of underestimated the value of
this more transpersonal like or mystical
and whatever kind of experiences and
they are therapeutically merciful as we
see right now with all the new trials
yes very interesting ok so I know our
time is drawing to a close together
which is a which is a shame from my
perspective means I don't think I would
ever have a finite set of questions to
ask you there would always be more it's
been really enjoyable talking to you so
I'm just rying to think of ways that we
could really provide value to people
here one would be to ask you what you
would recommend for people to read or
engage with that you think gives the
best introduction to but then moving
towards the potential for a
comprehensive understanding of how to
understand perhaps modern psychiatry
psychology but and where that intersects
with psychedelics yeah and so right now
there's not so much out there which
concert conceptualizes these kind of
relationships and so on and we also have
to realize that stan grof is out of
science since 40 years you know he's
more into conceptualizing things but
with not very much scientific foundation
anymore it's because of his huge
experience he can conceptualize things
without his scientific base of knowledge
and so therefore he can't be recruited
for that purpose and there are not so
much people in the field right now as
far as I can see which might be able to
do that and so we were it will be an
interesting time to see how psychiatry
might integrate these new approaches
which are in fact very old because we
were in charge of a cathartic procedures
in the former times hundred years ago
they used that much more in
psychotherapy and psychiatry but they
they changed their mind
have less feelings as our culture tends
to be to be bomb be more rational to
have less feelings and for example
psychoanalysis was gone away from
effectivity and up reaction and
catharsis because of not - of not coming
to near to the patient to become too
empathic which might be fall in love at
last these kind of things so they stayed
away from a pre action and more feelings
and I think that we there will be also
an revival of feelings as healing powers
in psychiatry and it is not so easy to
educate these this how should I say
old-fashioned or the psychiatrists of
today to educate them to allow more
feelings to allow more openness about
the inner processes which might be
activated by psychedelic drugs and
therefore I think there is a huge
skepticism which we will confront in the
future even if some people are
interested in these kind of things but
there is a lot of resistance we have to
go over in the future
ok ok so perhaps you might like to say a
few words about your upcoming book I
know this conversation will be released
a route well it will be released at the
appropriate time for a release of that
book so who should be interested in it
what's its name and yeah and it's a way
to say right now called the science of
micro dosing that's a book about micro
dosing and it gives you an impressive
overview about all we know about because
I'm you I shouldn't say that but it's
true I'm one of the leading experts in
respect to the pharmacology of LSD I
have written a book with Oxford
University Press about the pharmacology
of LSD and I really comprehensively know
all the literature about it and all the
facts and so therefore it might be
interesting especially for scientists
and for the serious potential micro
doses to know about the history because
I'm a historian - I'm into these
elaborating these methods - but I'm also
into pharmacology and
looking up all these little tiny studies
which have been done in the past and I
also can contextualize that with the
recent knowledge what we gained about
LSD I might also mention that we
recently founded the International
medical psychological society for
substance assisted psychotherapy which
will be an institution meant to to
evaluate a therapeutic procedures to
provide guidelines to do Quality
Assurance procedures and stuff like that
to find consensus about certain
therapeutic procedures and processes on
an international level so that we can
kind of setting the standards and norms
we have to take care of that because
otherwise we will not be established and
not come through in the established
communities of psychiatrists and
psychologists and so this would be an
important step and in connection to that
I might mention that I'm actually
writing another book right now which
will be or which is intended to be the
comprehensive textbook about psychotic
and psychedelic therapy and sorting all
these effects together even the most
modern approaches and the other
neurobiology and so on and so on and
this is because of having a kind of
multidisciplinary approach from my way
what I studied from social science to
philosophy to psychology and then
medicine and neurobiology so it is
sometimes good if you have one person
kind of sorry knowing everything and put
it together in a thing with what is kind
of straightforward and not having five
contributions where you replicate parts
here and as you repeat that there and so
on it has to be more kind of out of one
feather so you say no beautiful that's
that's super interesting I look forward
to both of those books I mean I
definitely will read him thank you so
much for doing this shake my hand please
it's really been a pleasure to us I will
have all the links to both where you can
get to the upcoming book get in touch
with everything to Austin's touched on
there in the show notes on the website
and also in the description in YouTube
thank you very much everyone and I would
like to thank you very much for being
such a noble intellectual thank you my
name is T Madeline by the way I never
actually had say Who I am but apparently
as important if you want to do the
bloody band so I'm going to do that
thank you very much to us and thank you
everyone
[Music]